Austin M. Putz – Curriculum Vitae

PERSONAL Information Austin M. Putz 231 Kildee Hall Iowa State University Ames, IA 50010 Cell: 1-515-249-6638 aputz@iastate.edu putz.austin@gmail.com LinkedIn Profile ResearchGate

Summary:

Background: Grew up on a diversified family farm in southern Iowa. Experience in most species except Dairy.

Experience: Took positions at three different genetics labs as an undergrad. Internships with Fast Genetics (on farm), Smithfield Premium Genetics (SPG) in R&D, and The Maschhoffs as a geneticist on special projects. Valuable experience to see real world breeding programs.

Classwork: Nine graduate level statistics courses. Many online (7) and in-class (2) animal breeding classes. Bioinformatics I and Immunology also.

Technical skills: Numerous technical skills gained during the M.S. and Ph.D. Includes R, Linux, bash scripting, LATEX, Julia, ASReml, SAS, and SQL.

Current: Ph.D. student with Dr. Jack Dekkers at Iowa State University working on disease resistance.

EDUCATION

Ph.D. in Animal Breeding and Genetics from Iowa State University (2015-2018(expected)). Thesis advisor: Jack C. M. Dekkers

Project on disease resistance in swine.

GPA: 3.78

M.S. degree in Animal Science from North Carolina State University (2013-2015). Thesis advisor: Mark Knauer. Committee: K. A. Gray (Smithfield), C. Maltecca (NCSU), H. Bondell (Stats NCSU). Thesis title: Alternative Litter Size Traits to Increase the Number of Weaned Pigs in Swine. Thesis

GPA: 4.0

B.S. degree in Animal Science from Iowa State University (2009-2013).

GPA: 3.93 (Summa Cum Laude)

Computer skills

Programming/scripting languages Advanced: R. Bash scripting Intermediate/Beginner: Julia, Python (3)

Genetic Software BLUPF90, ASReml, DMU (some), GenSel, JWAS (Julia)

Reporting LATEX(e.g. this CV)

Operating systems Extensive experience with Mac OS. Solid experience with Ubuntu (Debian). Some experience with Windows.

Servers Has successfully set up a home server (Ubuntu 16.04.1) to run genetic analyses (ssh, GenSel, BLUPF90, ASReml, R, Julia)

Databases Basic experience with SQL (SQLite)

Other GitHub, vim/awk/sed, SAS (modeling)

Open source projects Provide much of my code and help files through GitHub https://github.com/austin-putz

Work Experience

2015 - Intern Geneticist (Carlyle, IL) The Maschhoffs

2013 - R&D Intern (Rose Hill, NC) Smithfield Premium Genetics

2012-2013 - Swine Molecular Genetics (Ames, ISU) Dr. Chris Tuggle

2012 - Breeding & Farrowing Tech (Cando, North Dakota) Fast Genetics

2012 - Beef Genetics Lab (Ames, ISU), Dr. James Reecy

2011 - Soil Microbiology Lab (Ames, ISU), Dr. Kirsten Hofmockel

2010-2011 - Barn Crew Member (Ames, ISU) ISU Vet School

Teaching

Animal Breeding (undergrad) TA Spring 2017 under Dr. Bundy. Responsible for 1 lab section.

Swine Systems Management TA Fall 2016 under Dr. Stalder

Reproductive Physiology TA 2 semesters at NCSU

Organic Chemistry Tutor Spring 2012

Projects

All available on GitHub https://github.com/austin-putz

BLUPF90 wrapper Linux/Unix wrapper for BLUPF90 programs (many analyses)

BLUPF90 man pages man pages (Linux/Unix) for most BLUPF90 family of programs

vim syntax highlighting vim syntax highlighting for QMsim and BLUPF90

Honors & Awards

2016 Lauren L. Christian Graduate Fellowship (Dept AnS)

2016 Caine-Bogle Family Graduate Fellowship (CALS)

2015 Miller Graduate Fellowship (ISU)

2013 National Pork Board Scholarship

2012 Kenneth and Ruth Wagner Scholarship

2012 Arthur Molln Scholarship

2011 Lane Wells Scholarship

Publications

Putz, A. M., K. A. Gray, C. Maltecca, F. Tiezzi, and M. T. Knauer, A comparison of accuracy validation methods for genomic and pedigree based predictions of swine litter size traits in Large White and Landrace breeds, J. Anim. Sci (submitted)

Putz, A. M., K. A. Gray, C. Maltecca, F. Tiezzi, and M. T. Knauer, *Variance component estimates for alternative litter size traits in swine*, J. Anim. Sci **93** (2015). doi:10.2527/jas2015-9416 https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/26641035

Abstracts

Putz, A. M., J. C. S. Harding, F. Fortin, G. S. Plastow, and J. C. M. Dekkers, *A natural challenge model for disease resilience in wean-to-finish pigs*, (2017) Presented orally at ASAS Midwestern Section.

Putz, A. M., C. R. Schwab, A. D. Sewell, and J. C. M. Dekkers, *The effect of PRRS virus disesase outbreak on genetic parameters of reproductive performance in pigs*, (2016) Presented with poster at ICQG.

Putz, A. M., K. A. Gray, C. Maltecca, F. Tiezzi, and M. T. Knauer, Accuracies of genomic and pedigree based predictions for swine litter size traits in Large White and Landrace breeds, (2015) Presented orally at ASAS Midwestern Section.

Putz, A. M., K. A. Gray, C. Maltecca, F. Tiezzi, and M. T. Knauer, *Variance component estimates for alternative litter size and piglet mortality traits*, (2014) Presented orally at ASAS Midwestern Section.

SHORT COURSES

Programming and computer algorithms in animal breeding with focus on genomic selection and single-step GBLUP, (2014) University of Georgia

References

Jack C. M. Dekkers Distinguished Professor, ISU jdekkers@iastate.edu

Mark Knauer Assistant Professor, NCSU mtknauer@ncsu.edu

Clint Schwab Director of Genetics, The Maschhoffs clint.schwab@pigsrus.net

Kent Gray Lead Geneticist, Smithfield Premium Genetics (SPG) kent.gray@spgenetics.com

Chris Tuggle Professor, ISU cktuggle@iastate.edu